Often my timing and will could have
destroyed me. If I'd have gotten any
sooner, it would have crushed me.
>> Yes. We must be grateful for even when
God doesn't answer prayers and even when
God says no.
In fact, I would dare to say to you that
I shout more over closed doors than I do
open ones. Every situation that comes up
in my life that seems insurmountable, I
cast my cares on him because I
understand that everything God does is
strategic.
Little did he know
that today would not be like any other
day
when they led blind Bartimaeus
to his spot
and set him down
out of the way
close enough to the traffic to attract
attention
but not so close that he would be
trampled on by the crowd.
He sat in his spot
wrapped in his coat
against the morning breeze
his cup in his hand.
For you see, because he was blind in his
eyes
it had affected every area of his life.
His self-esteem, his masculinity
his income, his commerce
his marketability are all affected
because one thing has gone wrong in his
life.
And he has made a job out of being
dysfunctional.
Like all of us who don't get well
we create a ecosystem of survival that's
built around our dysfunction and some of
us refuse to get well because we fall in
love with being sick.
And they laid him
by the highway side begging.
And the scripture says the most amazing
thing. It says that he heard
that Jesus was passing by.
And when I read it, I couldn't help but
get excited because it reminded me that
God doesn't let everything go wrong at
the same time.
That even though the man couldn't see
he could hear.
And isn't it nice to know that God
doesn't need anything that you lost to
bless you?
That God will use what you've got left
to bless you.
That he'll take what is within close
proximity to you and allow you to hear.
He heard that Jesus was passing by. I
don't know how he distinguished the
sound of Jesus' footsteps from others,
but some kind of way he knew that it was
Jesus
that was passing by.
And he sensed something that is never
seen.
The fierce urgency of now.
Nobody told him that this would be the
last walk Jesus took.
That this would be the last chance that
he would have to get an earthly miracle
from an earthly Christ. That he was on
his way to Calvary.
And though he could not see he did not
lack vision.
They asked Helen Keller
what was it like to be blind? She said,
"It's not so bad to be blind. She said,
"It's far worse to have eyes and have no
vision."
This man had the vision
that if he didn't get it right now, he
wouldn't get it.
So, the first thing you got to have is
vision.
And then the second thing you got to
have is enough courage
to be disruptive.
He wasn't worried about being
politically correct fitting in being
popular, being accepted.
He wasn't worried about the tone of the
pitch of his voice. He was not afraid to
get loud.
He cried out, "Jesus, thou son of David,
have mercy on me. Oh, oh, oh, that I
might receive. I don't want a car, I
don't want a house, I don't want a
donkey, I don't want a goat, I don't
want to feel, I just want you to fix the
little thing that has shut down
everything in my life. And everybody has
a little thing that shut down everything
in their life. And if you fix this one
thing, I can fix the rest of it myself.
Oh, that I might receive my sight. And
the disciples that were with Jesus told
him to shut up.
But when you sense urgency, you can't
let man shut you down.
He cried all the more until he did
something that few in the Bible can ever
say they did. He cried out till God
stood still.
And there's somebody right now who needs
a miracle so bad that you need to cry
out until God stands still.
And the Bible said that Jesus stood
still in spite of his disciples making a
decision for him without him.
That he was too busy and too important
to have to stop and take care of the
needs of the blind man. Jesus stood
still. In other words, the cry of the
blind arrested the sights of Jesus.
Good God of mercy.
And he arrested him to the degree that
all of a sudden Jesus stood still and
commanded that he be called. Watch this.
He made the men who who forbid him from
coming have to turn around and call him.
Isn't it funny how God will make your
enemies your footstools? Isn't it funny
how God will use the very people who
didn't want you to holler anymore to
commanded them that he be called. He
made them reverse the curse.
And they told him
Jesus wants you. Now, this is what I
want to tell you.
He had to answer the call
blind.
Jesus didn't come to him.
And they didn't go get him.
They just called him.
And that means
that he had to go toward
Jesus
blind.
And I have learned over the 45 years of
my ministry
that most of the time
I was moving toward him
blind.
I couldn't see my way clear.
I didn't know how it was going to
happen.
I didn't know who I was going to hire.
I didn't know where I was going to go. I
didn't know what I would have to do.
But if you are willing
to go toward what you hear blind
God will do amazing things
in your life.
He went to him blind
but he didn't go from him blind.
Cuz once you make it to Jesus
he will make everything
all right.
Often when I'm not doing what I'm doing
here, I do seminars. I go and listen at
different people speak. Not just
preachers, but teachers. Not just
teachers, but thinkers. Not just
thinkers, but leaders. Not just leaders,
but business people. And when I go into
a business session, they always teach
that the best place to build a business
is around a problem.
Then if you find your problem, you found
your business.
Because if your business solves a
problem, you don't have to spend much
money marketing it.
You For example, you don't have to spend
a lot of money marketing hospitals.
Because it solves a problem
the fact that it is the answer is its
own marketing.
You don't have to market to a great
degree funeral homes
because there will always be clients
because there will always be death.
Anytime you find a business that solves
a problem, you are going to be
successful.
The reason our God has withstood the
test of time the reason the Bible is
still the best-selling book in the world
the reason that our God is called on on
every continent on this earth in one
language or another
is because he is the problem solver.
He is the mountain mover.
For every disease, he is the healer.
Too often we think that we know the
solution.
And we spend time and months and years
and sometimes decades
before we finally learn that we are not
as smart as we thought we were. And we
don't know as much as we think we know.
And we don't have as much as we think
that we have. And finally, with
humility, we bow our heads before his
grace and submit to his sovereign plan
and understand the manifold wisdom of
God. That God knows everything about
everything.
The grape does not say to the master
vintner
"Excuse me, but now is the right time to
act."
No, he hangs on the vine and waits
counting on the master to know when to
pluck me
and when to crush me
and when to convert me
and when to preserve me
because he knows when to do what in your
life.
There are some things that God gave me
now had he given me 20 years ago I would
have spoiled it. Right.
>> Had he given it to me 10 years ago I'd
have made a mess of it.
There are some things that God had to
put on hold for such a time as this that
I would be strong enough, old enough,
wise enough at the right season in my
life to master well enough what he's
given me. What about you? Are there
times in your life that you see God
giving you things now that you wanted
earlier but God held them back and let
you stay on the vine until it was time
to pull you at the right time to produce
what he wanted to produce in your life
because God has a clock that's not our
clock. His timetable is not our
timetable. His ways are not our ways.
His thoughts are not our thoughts and if
we just humble down and and get patient
enough to wait on him. They that wait
upon the Lord shall renew their
strength. They shall mount up on wings
like eagles. They shall run and not be
weary. They shall walk and not faint. Oh
God, teach me how to wait.
Teach me how to wait. Teach me how to
wait even if I have to just hang there
like a grape on a vine and wait. Teach
me how to hang on and wait on you cuz
you know just when to pluck me and you
know just when to pull me and you know
just when to expose me and you know how
much light I can bear.
And oh God, don't let anything shine on
me that's too bright for me.
Don't let anything shine on me that's
too hot for me.
Because the greater the light the
greater the heat.
Often my timing and will could have
destroyed me. If I'd have gotten any
sooner it would have crushed me.
We must be grateful for even when God
doesn't answer prayers and even when God
says no.
In fact, I would dare to say to you that
I shout more over closed doors than I do
open ones.
Because I trust God that he knows what I
can handle and what I can't handle and
if he says no I say thank you and if he
says yes I say thank you and I've
learned whatever state I'm in there with
to be content because he knows what's
best for me. Job said he knows the way
that I take and when he's tried me I
shall come forth as pure gold. I'm
turning it over to him. Every problem,
every situation, every crisis, every
every situation that comes up in my life
that seems insurmountable, I cast my
cares on him because I understand that
everything God does is strategic. Yes.
When the Bible says, "In the beginning
was the word and the word was with God
and the word was God." The word in the
in the Greek is logos and logos is more
than word, it's thought. It means that
everything that God is is well thought
out. It's well planned. He's not talking
out of the top of his head. He's talking
out of the depths of his will. And what
God has ordered will come to pass and he
has a strategy.
He has a strategy. He told his
disciples, he says, "There's a colt when
you get to the village and he's tied up
and he's waiting on you to come." He
knew where the colt was in another
village without going there because God
is strategic and he put the right colt
in the right place at the right time so
that Jesus could make his entry. A colt
that no man had ever sat on before
because God is a strategic God. I got to
stop cuz if I get to going down this
road I'm going to fool around and get
myself happy. God is a strategic God. He
knows how hot to make it. He knows how
cold to make it. He knows how tough to
make it. He knows what it takes to make
your son's will break. He knows what it
takes to bring your daughter into
submission. He knows what it takes to
heal your marriage. He knows what it
takes to bind up the wounds of your
broken heart and he knows when to do
what to get you where you need to be. He
always sees every problem before it
occurs. The master renter will use
anything to point you back to our need
for him.
For without him
I would just hang on this vine
until I die.
And thank you, Lord
for knowing when to pluck me
off the vine.
This night was like the night before the
night before that and the night before
that and the night before that and it
had become a routine ever since
ever since the old man's son had left.
He would peek in the room where he once
lie
and look at the bed he once slept in
and look at the pajamas he once wore
the cup he once drank from
and the plate he once ate from
and wonder
where is my child tonight?
I think not knowing is
is the most painful part of it.
Uncertainty
can almost be fatal.
And he couldn't help it but night after
night
he would go to the window
and peek out.
I know it's silly. I know it's crazy. I
know it's ridiculous.
But you cannot cut love off
with the turning of a switch.
And though he was gone
he still loved him.
And though he had spent his substance in
riotous living and ran out the door
belligerently
and gone about his own will and sought
himself a new family, a family filled
with friends and frolic
and foolishness
the old man knew that the friends and
the frolic and the foolishness was only
built around the finances
and as soon as he ran out of finances
the friends and the frolic and the
foolishness would all go away and maybe
just maybe
if he were humble enough
maybe
I'll get to see him come down that road
before God closes my eyes
and I never see him again.
And it had become his nightly routine.
It had become
his thoughts. It had overwhelmed him
like it overwhelms all of us anytime we
lose something that we love. It's
impossible to find the off switch to
stop caring about what we care about and
stop loving what we love and stop
needing what we need
until one night
while he was going through
what would seem like the waste of time
of going through the routine of the same
thing over and over and over again and
looking at the bed and looking at the
pajamas and looking at the plate and
looking at the cup and looking out the
window this time it was different
because when he looked
when he looked out the window
he saw a form in the shadows
and he knew by the gait of his walk
that that was his son.
And he opened up the door
and ran out on the front porch.
And something in his flesh told him to
stand there and be still and be proud
and make the boy grovel but something in
his heart said run.
And when you are old there are not many
things that will make you run.
But the sight of his son coming home
would make him run.
The star of the story is not the
prodigal son.
It is the relentless love of the father.
For the prodigal son fluctuates
and the elder brother is angry and the
only one stable in the whole story
is the father.
And the only one stable in your life is
the father.
No matter what state you're in, whether
you're in the dirty stage of being in
the ground or the growing stage of
coming up a plant or the fruitful stage
of budding and blossoming into volumes
and clusters of grapes or the crushing
stage of the painful regrets and
miseries and vicissitudes of life, I
want to assure you that whatever state
you're in
the star of your story is never your
process.
It's your promise of the father
that I will wait for you
until you find yourself.
And to somebody today that I'm speaking
to, I may not know your name, your
address, your phone number, your state
of where you come from. I may not know
the language you speak or what you have
on right now but the father told me to
tell you he's looking out the window
again.
And he's waiting on you
and he'll take you back
even if you smell like the hog pen
you've been in and he'll take you back
even if it means flies and gnats are all
around your head and he'll take you back
even if you have not been washed and the
old man ran out to meet him
and covered him with a robe of
righteousness that made him appear clean
Though underneath he was filthy and
sweaty and dirty. And he put the ring on
his finger to recognize that he was
still a part of the family.
And just before he let him back in the
house, he killed the fatted calf. For
without the shedding of blood,
there is no remission of sin.
And to God be the glory
because the blood sealed the deal.
The fatted calf died that the son might
live and brought him back into the house
again. And so may you join us in our
father's house.
Plucked, yes.
Crushed,
sometimes.
Bottled and constrained, yes.
But he has a place for you
at the table.
And he's waiting on you.
And he told me to say, "Come and dine."
The master called.
Come
and dine.